Guide to the Adolf Klainberg Papers on the Social Service Employees Union WAG.380
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Adolf Klainberg Papers on the Social Service Employees Union
1963-1978
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Klainberg, Adolph
WAG.380
1.67 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes
Adolf "Dolph" Klainberg is a retired labor organizer who was active in SSEU Local 371. Dolph began at SSEU in 1963, at the beginning of the organizing efforts within the union. He had been teaching at a junior high and was drawn toward social work. He was first hired within social services in the Bronx, but shortly thereafter ended up at the New York City Human Resources Administration - Dyckman Job Center. Dolph was a delegate and a union representative within the office at Dyckman. Through his role he attended delegate assemblies, organized along with many of the major events of the 1960s, and called attention to the basic concerns of working conditions in civil service jobs. The Adolf Klainberg Papers on the Social Service Employees Union (dated 1963-1978) consists of materials collected by Klainberg during his time organizing with SSEU Local 371 and his time working at the Dyckman Center. The materials document the Dyckman Center as an activist corner within SSEU. The materials include bylaws and constitutions, contracts, publications, leaflets from the 1960s through the 1970s, election ephemera within the union by year, collective bargaining documents, newsletters and newspapers.
Scope and Contents
The Adolf Klainberg Papers on the Social Service Employees Union (dated 1963-1978) consists of materials collected by Klainberg during his time organizing with SSEU Local 371 and his time working at the New York City Human Resources Administration - Dyckman Job Center. The materials document the Dyckman Center as an activist corner within SSEU. The materials include bylaws and constitutions, contracts, publications, leaflets from the 1960s through the 1970s, election ephemera within the union by year, collective bargaining documents, newsletters and newspapers.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Adolf Klainberg in November 2025; the accession number associated with this gift is 2025.096.
Biographical Note
Adolf "Dolph" Klainberg is a retired labor organizer who was active in SSEU Local 371. Dolph began at SSEU in 1963, at the beginning of the organizing efforts within the union. He had been teaching at a junior high and was drawn toward social work. He was first hired within social services in the Bronx, but shortly thereafter ended up at the New York City Human Resources Administration - Dyckman Job Center. Dolph was a delegate and a union representative within the office at Dyckman. Through his role he attended delegate assemblies, organized along with many of the major events of the 1960s, and called attention to the basic concerns of working conditions in civil service jobs.
Historical Note
Social Service Employees Union (SSEU) Local 371 is part of District Council 37 of the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), AFL-CIO. In January 1965, over 8,000 welfare workers went on strike for 28 days, a successful effort that earned the workers improved pay and benefits, a broad union contract, and real collective bargaining rights. During 1965 and 1967 SSEU strikes, there was significant internal discussion as to whether to remain independent or join the AFL-CIO. Significant victories in the union came in the form of establishing a pension system, and in developing the first citywide home care program. The union was deeply connected to social issues of the time period, including the 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom; anti-war demonstrations in Central Park and Washington, D.C.; and the war on poverty. Client groups that were represented at the Dyckman Center were focused on creating better standards of living in the city: housing, food, access to basic needs and necessities like clothing and rent deposits. The union helped to change city-wide policies around how funds for client groups could be provisioned and grew to include money for clothing, furniture, and housing.
Labor unions; Social service.; White collar workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Collective bargaining.; Klainberg, Adolph; Social Service Employees Union
- Constitution and Bylaws, 1963-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Collective Bargaining, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
- Elections -- 1960s, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Elections -- 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Elections -- 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Elections -- 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Elections -- 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Publications, 1966-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10-13, Box 2, Folder 1)
- National Federation of Social Service Employees (NFSSE), 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Client Groups and Community Action, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Daily Noose, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Militant Caucus, Progressive Labor, Socialist Workers Party, Worker Client Alliance, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Dyckman Center Publications, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Local Newsletters, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Treasurers Report, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Leaflets, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Leaflets, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Leaflets, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Leaflets, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Leaflets, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Leaflets, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Leaflets, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Leaflets, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Leaflets, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Leaflets, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Leaflets, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 9, Box 4, Folder 1)
- Leaflets, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Local Newsletters, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Contracts, 1965-1976 (Box 4, Folder 4-8)